Will it be be much longer?
Half an hour.
I don't like it when we print all night.
If a soldier were to pass by!
It never happens.
Once would be enough.
Marie, it's time to remove those,
they're dry.
How long will the guy who picks up
the leaflets at the station, wait for us.
Normally 5 minutes.
Is he a railwayman?
Jules! The less you know...
If he sets up a rendezvous
at the station, I suppose so.
It's not a bad place for a
clandestine rendezvous.
It will be fine.
It allows us to disseminate them
throughout the whole Department.
We're moving up to another level.
What's he doing!
He told us to wait,
and we're waiting for him.
He'll come.
We still look a bit silly waiting
for a train when there isn't one due.
At least there's no risk of missing the...
...the guy?
No, the train.
Do you think that's him?
I don't know.
Since there's no train.
Yes, that's him.
Don't look at him.
We'll wait.
Take me in your arms.
In the rubbish bin.
No one can see you, go on.
The train went. The Jews were still
on the platform guarded by the SS.
Did you note the train number?
No.
The number of the SS unit at least?
Not really, no.
Excuse me, but information like that
is too vague to be useful.
I'd really liked to have seen you there.
Is that a reproach?
Excuse me being Jewish,
and not able to go in person.
Who do you think the Jews we saw, were?
They must be the ones from Montbéliard.
Or Belfort, there've been
roundups in recent days.
The Boches will have intended them
changing trains, it happens all the time.
And you're sure you're not at risk?
I'm French, Pétain won't permit
them to touch French Jews.
Your wife is Austrian,
isn't she also at risk?
No, she's married to a Frenchman.
Did the guy pick up the briefcase?
Yes.
Well, that's the essential thing.
It was job well done.
A Boche car!
Shit, it's not our lot, it's the SS.
Surely you've not been followed?
No, of course not!
...to look for the Headmaster.
It's best I go before they
look for me in the cellar.
Find him...       Fast!
I don't know where he is,
I don't know how to help you.
Well hey, here he is.
I didn't know where you were.
I was excavating the cellar.
You must come with us.
What!
Why, I don't understand.
Hurry.
You haven't been informed?
There's the Headmaster.
Monsieur Bériot!
We've a little crisis.
80 foreign Jews, rounded up yesterday
in eastern towns, are stranded here.
They were in a German military train
which had to go elsewhere.
A new train will pick them up
in a day or two.
They're hungry and some are sick.
We need beds and sinks, that's why
I thought of the school.
It's the holidays and you don't
have any pupils.
There are fairly large rooms and you have all
those camp beds stored by the army in 1940.
Camp beds?
I... That doesn't seem likely
Monsieur le Maire.
How can there not be?
These camp beds are really in the cellar?
Yes, yes, it seems to me.
Well good then!
The school is the only building available.
I mean which has sanitation, running water...
But the school isn't a place of detention!
It's not for detention, they're in transit.
You don't have any pupils. Good God,
I don't understand you, Bériot.
But I've nothing to feed them!
I don't have towels or sheets.
We seized a warehouse of black market food
yesterday, that will be good for two days.
For the rest, we'll manage.
Listen, I had a hard time convincing
Servier and the Kommandant. They wanted...
...to dump them in the station waiting room
for two or three days. Can you imagine!
So what do you say?
I really don't see how.
There's a moment, Monsieur Bériot where you have
to think of other than your narrow personal interest.
There you are Larcher,
where are you with this?
I've outlined my idea to Monsieur Bériot
And... he agrees.
Let's be clear, this operation's
your responsibility.
You're in charge of the Jews' transport,
feeding, and especially surveillance.
A platoon of Gendarmes is en route.
Any escape would have very
grievous consequences.
On departure the Gestapo will count
the Jews. Do you understand?
Obviously. Don't worry, I'm not
going to traffic in Jews.
When you are going to bring them?
As soon as the buses are here.
I didn't tell you, there aren't any buses.
.. they'll have to make the journey on foot.
On foot!
Oh good!
We have two hours then.
Then I'll get organized.
Wait, I'll help you.
No!
Don't be childish.
You're pissing me off, leave me.
Finally, you see how you talk to me?
The more you try to help,
the less it actually helps.
Nice of you to tell me that.
I've washed and wiped you for months...
So, do you want a medal?
It's true you're making progress.
Listen, Raymond, it's a matter of patience.
The doctor said that again yesterday.
Screw you.
Who's this Chassagne you're
lunching with this afternoon?
How do you know?
I saw it in your notebook.
He's a business lawyer, very prominent
in Paris, and recommended by Papa.
He's coming to take over the Presidency
of the Chamber of Commerce.
He's going to help me with
administrative details.
Since when do we need a lawyer
to deal with this stuff?
Listen Raymond, I've been running the ship
for months and I don't think I'm doing badly.
It's still my business.
Yes, obviously.
What does that mean?
Nothing, but...
Nothing.
I want to come to the lunch!
With your crutches? You're joking,
you'll scare him.
I came to see if Monsieur needs anything.
Oh, no, Monsieur never needs anything.
Let me tell you, the next time
you tell Monsieur...
...about people I'm having lunch with,
it's the door. Understand?
...Damn it all.
Come on, the last trip.
It goes like this.
Set up the camp beds, and then
we'll see with the police.
After that, do you want us to
clean the cellar, Monsieur?
No, I'll take care of it myself.
Thank you for the offer.
Headmaster!
Stop!
Stop there.
You're the Headmaster?
Yes, Bériot.
Garin.
Morel!
Murat, Baudin...  get them into order!
In ranks of four, facing me.
On my command! Ranks of four!
I'm going to need the location plans.
Boiler room, cellar, and service spaces...
The Germans have all the plans.
The Germans?
They've had a barracks on that side
since September 40.
It's starting well!
Where do all these people come from?
No idea.
There'll never be enough beds.
What a mess!
If I knew the half-wit who had the idea
of stowing these people in Villeneuve!
Good day.
You could at least reply.
I've been up since five this morning,
you know...
Sleep well?
Yes, what was the phone call
that woke me this morning?
A problem at the Station.
Like what...?
Jews that no-one knew what to do with.
You're interested in the outside world now?
Daniel!
You're right, I'm interested
in nothing at the moment.
Everything seems empty to me...
...bland...
You should travel.
Henriette, already!
No, never before three o'clock.
Daniel!
Sarah!
Gosh!
Come in.
I can't believe it.
Sarah, what a surprise!
Madame.
But I don't understand. Last week
Servier told me it could last for months.
It was a German who came to free me.
The German proceedings against you,
instigated by Heinrich Muller have been stayed.
Good. You'll stay here then!
I don't want to disturb you, Monsieur.
Sarah you're joking, give me your bag.
I'll put them downstairs.
Yes, in her room.
Excuse me, but could I go
and wash my hands?
Of course Sarah, you're at home here.
Thank you.
Well, you're making a face!
You should be happy.
It's odd they've released her now.
No-one must know she's here.
Cancel my consultations,
for an emergency I'll go to the home.
Feed her, shelter her, but she can't
go out. She sees no one, understood?
But what do we do in the future?
I don't know, we'll see.
Does this give you a problem?
No.
... Can I count on you?
But yes, of course.
Ten... Fifteen in the first small room.
How many per bed?
One bed for four.
For families mostly...
They'll sleep in turns.
Four per bed!
These beds come from the cellar, right?
Yes.
Could there be others?
Oh no, no, no.
The other cellars are condemned,
there's a risk of an earth slip.
If you're afraid, I can go with my guys.
Oh no, no, I can't let you. I'd need permission
from the Academy, or I'd be for the high jump.
Yes, I'm going to find out.
Meanwhile, they'll thus be four to a bed.
Messieurs et Mesdames,
please let the car pass.
It's the Sous-Préfet.
I'm going to have a couple
of words with him.
Is it going well?
This is madness, Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
They're going to be packed like sardines.
I give it two hours before
sanitation breaks down.
It's fine for a few children from time to time.
Not for dozens of families continually.
What are you suggesting. Returning
them to the Station?
No!
Then welcome to the real world.
These people are not on holiday...
they're Displaced Persons in transit.
Reserve the beds for pregnant women,
children, the elderly...
...the others a blanket and the floor.
It's not complicated.
It's for two days.
The Jews won't move, Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
What do we do?
I'll talk to them.
Silence in the ranks, silence!
Silence, I said.
Excuse them but many of these people
don't speak French.
Yes well, we're in France here!
Please.
Messieurs et Mesdames, I ask you all
for your attention.
You'll be kept here...    In this school...
...until a new train arrives.
To go where?
Until a new train arrives and takes you
where the authorities...
... French and German, see fit.
You should tell us, this is unbelievable.
Monsieur, I've lived in France for 20 years.
My wife is French. Why have I been arrested?
I don't like your tone, Monsieur.
You're a foreign Jew?
Yes.
Under the Act of October 4th 1940,
you can be arrested at any time.
All this is perfectly legal.
What I ask of you all, including children...
...is to behave well, give your
name, marital status...
...and obey police orders. Any disobedience
would have dramatic consequences.
For you, as for us!
I appeal to your sense of responsibility.
Remember we've made a great effort
to accommodate you here.
Don't disappoint us!
Go ahead, make them enter the school.
We haven't got all day.
Go on, everyone enter the school.
The head of family will give the name of
each member, with date and place of birth.
And those who don't speak French?
Jews are smart, right?
They'll understand for sure.
Come on, arrange yourselves
in alphabetical order.
Give your names... Come on...hurry.
Bravo my dear, you'll triumph at the audition.
Was it good, Mistress?
Yes, Hélène, it was good.
Very good.
Good, take your friends into the garden.
Come on, we'll play at riddles.
Alright, but I'll ask the questions.
What's gone wrong Madame Crémieux?
Her performance just won't do!
I found it good.
Three big mistakes in rhythm, a forgotten
measure, she'll be ridiculous at the audition!
She must work. If you don't require her to...
You don't realize!
What?
But look....
Hélène hears they're arresting Jews everywhere,
and now they've even brought them to her school...
How do you expect her to work?
It would do her good to think
of something else.
To focus on music.
When I have cares, I think of my work.
It's not cares we have Mademoiselle!
Madame!
I'll see you out.
Monsieur Crémieux.
Good day.
Good day. The work with my husband
is progressing?
You have a project at the school?
Yes, a little digging in the cellars.
You know, your daughter is
very, very good on the violin.
Yes, I know.
Try to make her work.
Goodbye. Goodbye.
What an idiot!
You're exaggerating, Hélène loves her.
German children love Hitler!
What's this story of Jewish
prisoners at the school?
Roundups.
This time it's Montbéliard and Belfort.
You risk nothing, Anna,
you're married to a Frenchman.
You see. You made the right choice
preferring me to Meyerson
That's clever!
I'm invisible, but without me,
you can't live.
What am I?
Invisible?
Invisible.
You can't see me.
Without me you can't live.
What do you need to live?
I don't know... to eat?
Yes, but food isn't invisible.
No, it leaves crumbs.
There's spiritual food.
Is it that?
Let it drop, anyway that's not it.
I know! I'm invisible but
without me you can't live...
...it's love.
Yes, and no. That's not it.
It's invisible, and we can't
live without love.
Perhaps, but it's not love.
Good. Well then, what is it?
It's air.
The air?
Yes.
The air is invisible, and without air...
...we can't live.
Love was much better.
Excuse me, I'm the Headmaster...
Phyl Goldmuntz, of Besançon.
You're lucky to have cigarettes.
Want one?
No. No, no, no. I mean it's good
that you have some.
What you said just now.
Your wife's really French?
Yes. For ten generations.
My children too.
There's only me that's Dutch.
So what happened?
Well, I don't know exactly.
You know. These days they arrest
first and ask questions later.
Monsieur Goldmuntz!
Excuse me.
Where did you find it?
Everywhere.
They threw it on the ground.
The Sous-Préfet's going to drop
on us again.
It's a bunch of crap.
But that's not the problem, Loriot.
Who cares what's written on it.
The problem is it exists and it's
circulating, that's the problem.
A linotype machine doesn't go
unnoticed. Shit!
No...   Will we do a house to house search?
Yes?
Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
Messieurs.
Monsieur le Sous-Préfet I'm really sorry...
I've come to give you an
extremely important task.
You're aware of what's happening
at the school...
Don't the Gendarmes normally
deal with that?
The German want us to use
this opportunity...
...to arrest all foreign Jews
in Villeneuve.
They gave me a list.
There are 28 names.
So we must provide 28 Jews,
tomorrow or the day after.
In any case before the train leaves.
I'm committed.
I don't have the staff for that.
Well, sort it out, recruit auxiliaries.
Excuse me, but arresting Jews
is the German's job.
Not anymore, there's agreement
at the highest level.
After all, if they want foreign Jews,
they can take them.
In the list there seem to be...
Do your job!
And get sorted to make sure
there are 28.
I want a report every six hours.
Understood?
Messieurs.
Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
These Jews make shit for us
Whore!
Its a good job he didn't know
about the leaflets!
Keep an eye on this leaflet story for me.
Get me ten copies of the list,
and recruit five auxiliaries
Not a useless bunch like last time, please.
OK.
Excuse me boss, but...
Yes Vernet, what?
Arrest non-offending civilians,
we're supposed to do that?
Listen, we're supposed to do
what we're asked.
Is that clear?
I want everyone here in an hour.
You're crazy to come here!
Who is it, darling?
A customer.
What will you take?
You're obsessed with security,
it's not normal!
There are French Jews among
the Jews in the school.
There are French? Now?
It's not possible!
Albert, I spoke with one of them, his
wife's French, children too.
They're all there.
Obviously the Boches have changed strategy.
I really don't know!
I just wanted to warn you.
But I know all that, I know.
I told you Anna's not at risk.
Good, well it's up to you.
I'm sorry to have bothered you.
Good. As for my project,
we'll work on it tomorrow, eh?
Fortunately, you're not a comedian.
See you later.
Already gone?
Yes.
A customer at the house,
I hope you told him off.
Oh, he's not likely to come back.
Listen, I've got news.
On the roundups?
I don't want to dramatize, believe me,
but it could...
Well, I have to say there could
be a danger for you.
Of arrest?
It's very unlikely, and I have
the situation in hand...
...but I don't want to take any chances.
I'd rather you go go for
a week or two in Switzerland.
At Irene's.
To Switzerland? How would I get there?
I know someone who can get you
across without a problem.
No risk.
With Hélène?
No, the crossing would be too
complicated with a child.
We'd tell her you're going to rest,
to see a friend...
But I don't understand, you just
told me I risked nothing.
What's happened in the last while?
Nothing, I had a customer on the phone.
A cop I sold binoculars to, a month ago.
He says the arrests are intensifying.
It's just for safety.
Can't it wait until after the audition.
It's next Tuesday?
No.
Pack your things for tomorrow, in time
to contact the passer.
Tomorrow!
You're scaring me!
Anna, there's no risk.
So!   You arrest the Stateless, Germans,
Austrians, Poles, Czechs and Russian Jews.
Not others, unless they're in breach
of the law, of course.
And in case of doubt about nationality?
Arrest them, Servier can clean it up later.
The sick?
Loriot, we haven't the time or skill
to separate fakers and the genuine article.
Bring them in...  Unless it looks
contagious, of course.
And kids?
What about the kids?
Given their age, some will have
been born here so they're French.
What do we do about them?
In that case don't arrest them, there's
no question of arresting French people.
If both parents are foreigners, we can't
leave a two year old alone in an apartment.
Well, in that case it's up to you to see
if the mother wants to keep it with her.
It's good for our quota, if not I don't know.
They give it to a friend, a neighbor, whatever.
OK?
If it's too complicated send them here.
We'll sort it out. It's simple.
Yes?
Messieurs.
Monsieur le Maire.
I'm told you're going to arrest
families within the Commune.
At the request of Sous-Préfet Servier, yes.
The majority of the Police
are still paid by the town.
...that is, by me.
Technically, yes.
It's out of the question
to arrest innocent families.
Nothing in the Armistice Agreement
requires us to do this.
Excuse me, but my Superior
tells me the exact opposite.
He's written to me...
Monsieur, Please give all your aid to
the arrest of foreign Jews.
Signed: Le Préfet de Région.
Well, "give all your aid" Marchetti,
But without my municipal police.
Excuse me, Monsieur le Maire, but...
The guys are family men,
they need their pay.
You overstep your rights there.
If I inform Servier that you oppose
a direct order, you'll be dismissed.
OK, meeting over. Go, go.
Furthermore, I see Sarah Meyer's on the list.
She serves at your house, right?
Yes...
...She's in administrative detention.
Might I know where?
I don't know.
As for Servier I'll go find him. I guarantee
it won't happen like that, believe me.
I doubt it.
Te Quiero isn't here?
No, he's with my mother in Besançon.
She adores him.
But he'll be there on Sunday.
I don't know if you'll recognize him.
It's amazing how he's grown.
Anyway.
Sarah, you're not well?
No, it's been like this for...
...for the last few weeks.
You should eat something.
No, I can't swallow anything.
Later, perhaps.
I'm pleased you were released.
Ah, it must be Daniel.
Madame!
Good day Henriette.
Good day.
Wait for me there.
I have an unexpected visitor, Henriette.
An unexpected visitor?
Yes. I have my niece from Besançon.
Her mother, my sister, sent her to me.
We're going to try to do something with her.
In town, she only thinks of boys.
That's girls today.
I tell you this because she'll be giving
us a hand with housekeeping this week, so...
...I won't need you, but I'll
pay you your wages, of course.
OK.
I'm sorry, not to have told you earlier.
It doesn't matter, I'll come back
on Monday then?
Yes of course, thank you Henriette, Monday.
Oh shit!
I'm sorry.
Monsieur...
I know you don't
like us helping you...
...but that's my job.
No, stop.
Are you sure?
To be honest, I'm thinking of someone else.
I'm thinking of someone else too.
...but it doesn't matter.
Who are you thinking about?
My cousin.
He was killed in June 1940.
No.
I still want to retain some illusions.
You're getting too old for that,
Monsieur Raymond.
As you wish.
This guy that my wife's eating
with at mid day...
Yes?
Chassagne...
Has he been here before?
He's been two or three times.
He does the accounts with Madame.
Sometimes late at night,
they both laugh a lot.
They laugh!
In all honesty, Monsieur, I have
to tell you.
You don't need all that?
Yes, yes.
You know, in flight...
It ensures that...
I want to keep my daughter with me.
To stay together...
OK.
This is good, there's everything you need.
The mother prefers to take her
little one with her.
Well, it starts out very hard.
And the old man?
Can you walk Monsieur?
In French, please.
In French!
He doesn't understand French.
He can't get out of this chair either.
So, what are we going to do?
Nothing... in the...
Maman!
To the right...
Get going. Hurry, hurry, go!
Loriot, I don't have all day here.
You have three there.
Go on!
So?
Sarah is sleeping?
Yes, yes, she's exhausted.
She's on a list of foreign Jews
to be arrested.
By the French police!
You can't do anything?
Oh you bet I called the Préfet. He made it clear
that if I called him again I'd be dismissed.
Marchetti is a better politician than me.
I told Henriette not to come this week,
but she saw Sarah.
So I told her she was a niece,
and I think she believed me.
Good, it just remains to tell Gustave then.
Do you think the Schwartzes
would take him for a few days?
We had Marceau for a week at
Christmas,so they may well do that.
And I'd rather change Sarah's room.
Here on the ground floor with patients and
visitors, someone will eventually see her.
Do you want her to take my room, Daniel?
Yes, it would be better.
She'll live on the second floor.
At least until curfew.
Yes.
You're right.
But it'll embarrass her to take my room.
Oh, I think she'll make an effort.
You can use it as soon as she wakes up.
Well, bravo!
You're poking about in my business now.
And you're tampering with mine.
Your father bought back the loan
from the bank?
I don't like the tone you're taking.
Its lucky I tampered with your
business, Raymond.
What does that mean?
Firstly it means that it cost a lot
to bury the Caberni affair.
And very expensive again to clean up
your crazy agreements with Crémieux.
There was nothing crazy about it.
Look! Imagine if the Germans discovered...
...their main Villeneuve subcontractor
was funded by Jewish capital.
You've taken advantage
to increase the capital...
...and now your father
has a majority share.
Obviously Papa's money bought back
the loan, he wasn't going to do it for free.
You have to understand that.
Let me go!
You really are a child.
I liked it best before.
2 Rue Basse, and 3 Rue Bassano.
We're at eleven.
Counting five in Rue Ancel.
In fact, the old man
with the wheelchair is dead.
He had a cardiac arrest in the van.
Where are you?
For now, zero.
Rue St Martin, no-one home.
I left the statutory notice...
...and at Rue des Cordeliers
they were Romanian.
Romanian, Polish, frankly its six of one,
half a dozen of the other.
I don't know. We have a list of
nationalities, I'm just the order taker.
Anyway this list is rubbish.
Our old files, poorly completed by the
Gendarmes and poorly assembled by the Boches.
Hello Henriette.
Inspecteur.
I don't know if this really
a good day for mopping the floor.
Oh, you know, it's never a
good day for mopping.
Loriot!
Yes.
Why is Ma Morhange there?
Failure to wear a yellow star.
She was arrested at a checkpoint.
Morhange, with an H after the R.
Hello, Judith.
Ah, Inspecteur, good morning.
Give me the file, I'll deal with it.
Follow me.
Sit down, please.
Have you seen our new premises?
Yes.
It's a change from your time.
Yes, it's...
So Judith...
What happened to you?
Ah, what happened to me!
Yes, failure to wear the yellow star
is serious.
Can I explain?
I returned to Villeneuve to
take care of some business...
...before joining my family in Toulouse.
I had all the papers,
and my train was at 5 o'clock.
But for Jews, the curfew's at 4,
so what to do?
If I put on my yellow star I'll be
arrested because I'm out after curfew...
If I don't put on, I am arrested for
not wearing the star.
Admit that it's absurd.
Weren't you supposed to marry de Kervern?
Because I was told you were
finding perfect love in Paris.
I'm here because of my yellow star,
not to tell you my life story.
You're here for whatever I want, Judith.
Is that clear?
You know, not wearing the star
right now is...
It's not good.
Good. So?
You're not married!
Yes, but it didn't work out.
Where is he now?
I don't know.
It's you who left him, I'll bet?
Listen, Marchetti, what are you
playing at now?
Answer my question.
Is he perhaps drinking again?
It's not that?
You're just as he said.
Meaning?
You like to make people suffer.
Henri said it was the way
you evade loneliness.
You know that he liked you.
Good, you're going to let me go?
Here's Judith Morhange...
...for failure to wear the yellow star.
Morhange with a H?
Yes.
You can go.
Thank you.
M O R H A N G E
You can take her.
Go. Find a place.
Good morning, Madame, come in.
Thank you.
Why won't Maman be there
for the audition?
I told you, she's taking
a short holiday, she's tired.
Tell her you're tired.
I'm tired.
Can't she wait until Wednesday to rest?
No. Eat.
Eat, darling.
I thought hearing me was important to you.
Obviously it's important.
But at the moment travel is very expensive
and you can't always choose the day.
If I could have arranged for her to be
at the audition, I would have done.
Now that's enough. Eat, or
I'll have to punish you.
You don't like the soup?
Yes, yes.
I know you wanted to help these
people Monsieur le Maire...
Have they eaten?
The Gendarme will arrive
in a moment with the first load.
I was told French police
are going to arrest Jews?
Excuse me Monsieur le Maire,
but I've come to know you.
I know you're a good man...
How can you condone that?
Here's Garin, go see him.
He's not bad for a policeman.
I hope he has the baby formula.
So the pick-up was good?
You're going to see!
We forced entry into the depot
explaining why we needed food supplies.
And this is all there was.
We're left with a hundred people,
locked in for an indefinite time,
...and nothing to feed them with!